[The Age of Awakening]
[觉醒年代]
[Episode Ten]
[第十集]
The internationally recognized
全世界都公认的
[Yi Baisha, styled Yuecun, Scholar of the New Culture Movement]
[易白沙 字 越邨 新文化运动学者]
figurehead of the Chinese people
中国人的灵魂人物
[Chen Duxiu, styled Zhongfu, Dean of Liberal Arts at Peking University]
[陈独秀 字 仲甫 北京大学文科学长]
is now being manipulated
现在却被一个个军阀
by the various warlords.
玩弄在股掌之中
[Zou Yongcheng, styled Qizhi]
[邹永成 字 器之]
This country is finished.
这个国家完了
It's ruined.
烂透了
Baisha.
白沙
[Wang Mengzou, Manager of Yadong Library]
[汪孟邹 亚东图书馆经理]
You are an educated person.
你是一文化人
You are not suited for politics.
不适合搞政治
Please do not plunge into despair.
你千万不能陷到这个旋涡里
How about you join me to teach at Peking University?
这样 你跟我去北大教书
We'll work together on "New Youth"
我们一起编《新青年》
to rebuild the citizen's mindset.
来重建国民的新思想
No, no, no.
不不不
Zhongfu, I won't follow you to Peking University.
仲甫 我不跟你去北大
I am telling you.
我要告诉你
What you said about avoiding politics for twenty years is wrong.
你说的二十年不谈政治行不通
It's impossible!
行不通啊
What's left is to fight with this ruined society.
现在只有跟这个烂透的社会拼了
I will fight with all my life.
拿命跟他们拼了
Brother Mengzou! Brother Mengzou!
孟邹兄 孟邹兄
Mr. Liu.
柳先生
Welcome, welcome!
欢迎欢迎
This is Mr. Zhongfu.
仲甫先生在
Nice to meet you, Mr. Zhongfu.
仲甫先生好
Mr. Liu.
柳先生
Brother Mengzou,
孟邹兄啊
I've heard that Mr. Zhongfu has arrived in Shanghai from Beijing.
我听说仲甫先生从北京来上海了
I've come to see him.
我过来看一看
That's great, welcome.
好好好 欢迎欢迎
I hope I'm not inconveniencing anyone.
我没影响你们吧
No, you are not.
没有没有没有
Please come in.
那 那进来 来来来
Let's sit inside.
我 我们屋里坐
Quick.
快请
Inside, inside.
屋里 屋里
Chat inside.
屋里聊
Mr. Meng.
孟先生
Chat inside you two.
好 你们聊
Please sit.
快请坐
Come. Come.
来来 来
Thank you
谢谢
Mr. Zhongfu, please excuse this small gift.
略备薄礼 还请仲甫先生笑纳
You are too gracious.
您太客气了
Please sit.
请坐
Alright.
好 好
Mr. Zhongfu.
仲甫先生
I am here to discuss with you,
我来是想跟你商量商量
matters involving the children.
孩子们的事
Now the country is facing internal strife.
现在国内吧 时局混乱
Because of Zhang Xun's restoration, classes have stopped.
因为张勋复辟 学校停课
Even if we resume classes,
如果再复课
it will be during the next semester.
那又是下一个学期了
Countless wars are happening overseas.
这国外呢战乱不断
So they want to go to France to work and study.
所以他们要到法国去勤工俭学
I'm afraid we can't provide a schedule at such short notice.
恐怕短时间内提不上日程
Mr. Liu, what do you intend to do then?
那柳先生有什么打算呢
I do not want to disrupt our children's futures,
我是不想耽误孩子们的前程
so I was thinking if both our families can work together
所以我想 我们两家能不能合作
and send the three of them to America to study.
把三个孩子送到美国去留学
I'll handle the paperwork
手续我来办
and expenses.
费用 我也可以承担
Mr. Liu,
柳先生
this is already the second time you have brought this up.
这已经是您第二次提这事了
I appreciate your concern
我很感谢您的美意
and understand your feelings,
也理解您的心情
but I will tell you frankly
但是 我还是要坦率地告诉您
I cannot agree to this.
这事并不可行
All these things.
这些东西
I think Mr. Zhongfu
我想仲甫先生
has prepared for Yannian and Qiaonian right?
定是给延年和养年准备的吧
Yes indeed.
是是是
Parents want the best for their children.
可怜天下父母心哪
Mr. Zhongfu, Liu Mei is my only daughter,
仲甫先生 柳眉是我唯一的女儿
so I understand how you feel.
所以 我感同身受
I can really understand
我特别理解
a father's love for his children.
一个父亲对孩子的良苦用心
But Mr. Zhongfu,
但是仲甫先生
regarding this matter,
在这件事情上
why are you so steadfast in your choice?
你为什么这么武断
Mr. Liu, please do not misunderstand.
柳先生集 您别误会
I'm not being steadfast.
不是武断
Firstly, I'm not able to decide on Yannian's behalf.
一是我做不了延年的主
Secondly, Yannian
二是延年这孩子
will never accept
他是绝不会接受
others' help.
别人的资助的
Let me tell you honestly,
说心里话
I'm worried about his attitude
我现在担心的就是他这态度
because Yannian
因为延年这个孩子
is too disciplined and confident.
太自律 太自信
I am not able to convince him.
我说不了他
I feel extremely guilty
惭愧得很
that, as his father,
我这个做父亲的恰巧在他面前
I have no right to speak.
也是最没有话语权的人
Mr. Zhongfu,
仲甫先生
the two children
你看两个孩子吧
are already in a relationship,
他们现在已经是这种关系了
so I feel that,
所以我觉得
as elders,
我们做长辈的
we should care about their future.
应该去关心一下他们的前程
This is an issue.
这倒是个问题
The two children
现在这两个孩子
are in what kind of relationship?
到底是什么关系
They--
他
I'm not sure if I can explain it clearly.
我现在有点说不清道不明
I understand
明白
Mr. Liu, how about this.
柳先生，这样
I'll talk to him.
我找机会问问他
We need to establish the facts first,
这个凡事要先搞清楚性质
so we don't make any mistakes.
才不至于出错
Let me handle it.
这事交给我了
After I get an answer,
等我问出结果之后
we'll speak again.
我们再谈 好吗
Thank you so much.
拜托了
You're too gracious.
您客气了
I'll take my leave first.
那我就先告辞了
Why don't you stay for a meal.
要不留下一块吃饭吧
No, no, no.
不不不
I know you haven't finished your previous discussion.
我知道 你这儿还有事没谈完
No need to send me off.
不送 不送
Alright, take your time.
好 好 慢走
I'll wait for your response.
我等你消息
Alright.
好
Baisha!
白沙
On the day of Zhang Xun's restoration,
张勋复辟当日
Li Dazhao was forced to leave Beijing.
李大钊被迫逃离北京
For several months, he was exiled in Jiangnan
他在江南流亡数月
and fell to the lowest rungs of society
广泛深入社会底层
to observe national sentiments
考察国情
and to clear his thoughts,
清理思想
desperately finding a way to save his country.
苦苦追寻新的救国之路
The Zhang Xun Restoration
张勋复辟
signaled that
宣告了在中国
the plan for the establishment of a bourgeois republic in China
建立资产阶级共和国的方案
failed completely.
彻底流产
The painful lesson
惨痛的教训
[Li Dazhao, styled Shouchang]
[李大钊 字 守常]
hastened the reform of the bourgeois
促使人们对资产阶级革命
and caused a change in perception and criticism.
进行反思与批判
The modern Chinese
先进的中国人
started to realize
开始认识到
that simply relying on transplanting
仅仅靠通过移植
Western political ideology and methods
西方政治制度的办法
cannot save China.
难以救中国
Saving China would require starting from the basics.
要从根本上改造中国
Apart from a cultural awakening
除了文化觉醒
and enlightenment,
和思想启蒙
listening to the voices of the people is crucial
还要倾听大众的呼声
to find a suitable solution to reform China.
找到符合中国实际的革新之路
Come here.
来 这儿这儿这儿
Zhongfu!
仲甫
Where is he?
这人呢
Uncle Wang!
汪伯伯
My father wouldn't have left right?
我爸不会走了吧
No, he wouldn't have
那不会
He would not have left before seeing the both of you.
没见到你们呢他不会走
[Chen Yannian, Chen Duxiu's eldest son]
[陈延年 陈独秀长子]
Even if he had left, he wouldn't have gone far.
走也走不远
Would he have gone to Jixi
不知 去绩溪了
to see Hu Shi?
见胡适去了
I told you we shouldn't have come.
我就说不来吧
Qiaonian, let's go.
乔年 走
Older brother!
哥
Yannian!
延年
These are the buns your aunt steamed.
你们姨妈蒸的包子
I was afraid it would spoil in the hot weather so I heated it up again.
天热我怕坏了 在展上再热热
Come.
来来来
Yannian, come.
延年 延年 过来
Listen to Uncle.
听佰伯话啊
Come.
过来 来来来
Sit here.
坐这儿 坐这儿 坐
Sit.
坐下啊
Look.
你看看
I told you he hasn't left yet.
我说没走吧
He went to steam buns for you.
给你们蒸包子去了
Yesterday,
昨天一来
your father said
你父亲就说
to send these buns to school.
把这个包子送到学校去
Gao Junman helped me to steam it.
高君曼 给我蒸的
She told me to eat it while travelling.
叫我路上吃
It's quite a lot, so help yourself.
挺多呢 你们吃吧
Come let's eat.
来来 吃吧 吃吧
It's meat.
肉的
Please eat, your aunt steamed it for you.
吃 你姨妈给你们蒸的
[Chen Qiaonian, Chen Duxiu's second son]
[陈乔年 陈独秀次子]
Didn't you say it was meant for you.
你不说给你蒸的吗
There are two different fillings,
蒸了两样馅
vegetarian and meat.
一个素的一个肉的
I've finished the vegetarian filling.
素的我吃完了
The meat filling is for you.
肉的给你们的
Can you stop pretending?
你能不能不装
Since when was there vegetarian fillings?
什么时候有素馅的
Why do I not know about them?
我怎么不知道
You have eaten them.
你吃了
Your aunt steamed these buns for you.
这就是你们姨妈给你们蒸的
He intentionally left them for you.
他没舍得吃 给你们留的
So please help yourself to them.
你们吃 吃吃
Come, eat.
来 来 吃
Just to eat some buns
吃个包子
and you had to lie about vegetarian fillings.
你还整出什么素馅什么的
Stop pretending.
装什么装啊
Speak honestly.
好好说话
I've finally managed to see you this time.
我这次来既然见到你们了
So let's chat.
就跟你们聊聊
Let's chat about two things.
聊的问题有两个
Firstly, the both of you have come out
第一 你们哥俩小小年纪
to see the world at such a young age.
就出来闯荡世界
Makes me relieved to see the both of you so self-reliant.
自食其力 我很欣慰
You want to go to France to work and study.
你们想去法国勤工俭学
I am supportive as well.
这个我也很支持
But now there is a world war going on.
但是现在是世界大战
The plan of staying in France is still far away.
留法的事情还遥遥无期
Our country is also experiencing internal strife.
国内也很混乱
You can't always remain
你们不能总是待在这个
at this French language centre.
法文补习班吧
If you do not have a long term plan, you will definitely have worries.
人无远虑必有近忧
I want to know
我就很想知道
what your thoughts are.
你们到底是怎么想的
Both of us will walk this path alone.
我们哥俩自己的路自己走
We won't rely on others and our family.
既不依靠别人 也不依靠家庭
To us, work-study
勤工俭学对我们来说
is the most appropriate path.
是最合适的路
We plan to study in France.
我们俩准备到法国去留学
We have a very strong foundation now,
现在已经有了很好的基础
we will not give up halfway.
肯定不能半途而废
So we have decided to remain in Shanghai to study.
所以我们决定留在上海上学
Yadong Library's business is doing well.
现在亚东图书馆的生意不错
We should be able to work-study with no issues.
我们勤工俭学没有问题
Most importantly we have many books to read here.
关键是这儿有我们读不完的书
We can't bear to leave.
我们也舍不得走
That's right.
对
We can go to Beijing during the holidays.
等我们放假的时候可以去北京玩
Alright, since you have already thought hard about it,
行 既然你们都已经想清楚了
I will respect your wishes.
那我尊重你们的意愿
Secondly,
第二个问题
can you tell me
你能跟我说说
what your relationship is with Liu Mei?
你跟柳眉到底是怎么回事吗
What do you mean?
什么怎么回事
Don't you think that
你不认为
everyone is curious about it?
大家都很关注这个问题吗
I'm not surprised that people are curious.
大家关注这个问题我不意外
I did not expect you to be curious about it as well.
我没想到你也会关注这种问题
Why not?
为什么
Because I feel that you
因为我觉得
are not such a superficial person.
你不是这么世俗的人
Is it superficial for me to be concerned about you and Liu Mei?
我关注你和柳眉的事情就世俗了
Since you are as superficial as everyone else,
既然你跟大家一样都这么世俗
I will tell you clearly
那我可以明确地告诉你
that I, Liu Mei and Qiaonian
我 柳眉 还有乔年
have a pure and noble relationship
我们是一种纯洁高尚的
based on mutual cooperation.
互助合作关系
I don't quite understand.
没太懂
Have you read Kropotkin's
那你看过克鲁泡特金
and Tolstoy's books?
和托尔斯泰的书吗
Yes I have.
看过
So you must know about mutualism,
那你应该知道互助主义
anarchism,
无政府主义
and pan-laborism.
和泛劳动主义
I know a little.
知道一点
So you should know about
那你也应该知道
what is mankind's ideal state.
人类社会最理想的状态是什么
I'm all ears.
我洗耳恭听
Mankind's most ideal state
人类社会最理想的状态
is when the whole society
是全社会所有的人
continuously achieves moral self-improvement
都会通过自律来不断地实现
through self-discipline.
道德的自我完善
Everyone will work together
所有人都结成一种
and form a relationship that transcends familial and romantic ties.
超越家庭和恋爱的友爱关系
Oh, so you and Liu Mei have this sort of relationship.
你和柳眉是这样一种关系
This is what I desire.
这是我追求
Then, other people get the impression
那在别人眼里
that you and her are a couple.
你们是一对啊
A couple?
什么一对
Like butterfly lovers, do you understand?
就是蝴蝶成双啊
Mandarin ducks or something, you know?
鸳鸯什么的一对 懂吗
This is the difference in our generations.
这就是我们两代人的不同
Your generation can't get rid of the obstacle of superficiality.
你们还无法摆脱世俗的鹦伴
But to us,
但对我们来说
that is our goal.
那正是我们要冲破的落禽
What we desire
我们追求的
is an eternal pure and noble friendship.
是永远纯洁高尚的友谊
Does Liu Mei have the same understanding as you?
那你要冲破这潘窝柳眉理解吗
Of course.
她当然理解
Additionally, I am
而且我现在
imposing a self-discipline rule on myself.
正在制定一个自律守则
I call it the six prohibitions.
我称它为六不
What do you mean?
什么六不
They are no skiving, no watching of shows, no photography,
分别是不闲游 不看戏 不照相
no eating at restaurants, no talking about fashion
不下馆子 不讲衣着
but most importantly,
最重要的是
no dating, no private relationships.
不谈恋爱 不作私交
If society is able to be disciplined
全社会所有的人通过自律
and continuously self-improve,
不断实现道德的自我完善
everyone will come together
所有人要结合成一种
to form relationships that transcend familial and romantic ties.
超越家庭 恋爱的友爱关系
So doesn't that make me and your aunt,
那这么说我跟你姨妈
your aunt and your Uncle Wang,
你姨妈跟你汪佰佰
your Uncle Wang and you,
汪佰佰跟你们
Liu Mei and I,
我跟柳眉
Liu Mei's parents and your aunt,
柳眉她爸妈跟你姨妈
the same type of relationship?
都是一种关系喽
That would be it.
应该是
Then why do you address your aunt as mother?
你为什么叫你姨妈姨妈
That's just a name.
那就是个称谓
So what do you call me then?
那你怎么称谓我呀
I've always called you Chen Duxiu.
我一直叫你陈独秀
Mr. Chen Duxiu.
陈独秀先生
Alright, I'll leave, please continue eating.
好 你们吃吧 我走了
Zhongfu.
仲甫
Zhongfu, where are you going?
仲甫 你去哪儿
I'm going back.
我回去了
Going back where? You didn't even bring your luggage.
你回哪儿去 行李都没带
Here's some more.
还有一盘
Eat up.
吃吧
This was given by Mr. Chen Duxiu,
对了 陈独秀先生带来的
steamed by Ms. Gao Junman.
高君曼女士蒸的
14 August 1917
一九一七年八月十四日
Duan Qi Rui announced
段祺瑞宣布
China's declaration of war against Germany and Austria,
中国正式对德国 奥地利宣战
joining the Allies
加入了第一次世界大战中的
in World War I.
协约国行列
The allied countries and America
协约国和美国
promised the Chinese government that
相继向中国政府保证
they will sponsor China
尽力赞助中国在国际上
and allow China to receive the benefits she deserves.
享得大国当有之地位及其优待
[Peking University]
[北京大学]
Here! Pass it here!
来了 搁这儿
Yucai is indeed something else.
豫才就是豫才
What type of writing can be
什么叫
far-reaching, deep in content, concise yet majestic?
立意深远 蕴含丰富 简洁大气
This is exactly the type of work!
这就是
[Qian Xuantong, styled Deqian, Professor at Peking University]
[钱玄同 字 德潜 北京大学教授]
Filled with strong literary spirit and style.
透露着浓厚的书卷气和文人风格
[Liu Shipei, styled Shenshu, Professor at Peking University]
[刘师培 字 申叔 北京大学教授]
An absolute masterpiece!
绝对是不可多得的精品
Look at it.
看看 都看看
[Shen Yinmo, Professor at Peking University]
[沈尹默 北京大学教授]
Yinmo, you're a great calligrapher and you understand the arts.
尹默 你是大书法家 懂美学
Tell everyone what this seal means.
跟大家说说 这个徽章的立意
My verdict is that it is extraordinary.
我的评价 超凡脱俗
Look at this seal.
你们看这个徽章啊
The words "Beida" (=Peking University) written in seal script are written vertically.
以北大两个篆字上下排列
The "Bei" at the top
上面的北
is written such that it looks like two people with their backs facing each other.
是背对背 两个侧立的人像
The "da" at the bottom
那下面的大呢
looks like a man standing straight.
是正面站立的人像
This is a man carrying two people on his back,
这是一个人肩负着两个人
which then symbolizes a meaning of a crowd.
也就构成了三人成众的意象
This shows that professors of Peking University
这也反映我们北大人
are shouldering the heavy responsibility of educating the people.
肩负着开启民智的重任哪
Good!
好
Well said!
说得好
In my opinion, these two words
依我看 这两个字
also has a symbolic meaning of being the pillar of society.
还有这个脊梁的象征意义
[Gao Yihan, Professor at Peking University]
[高一涵 北京大学教授]
Does it look like
像不像
Mr. Zhou put "Bei" and "da"
周先生把北和大
to make it seem like a man's spine?
做成了一具非常形象的脊梁骨
He is trying to convey that Peking University
他是想表达我们北大人
should become the backbone of this country,
应该成为国家
shouldering the progress and democracy of this society.
民主和进步的脊梁的意思
Wrong. Wrong.
非也 非也
Too far-fetched.
牵强附会
What you said is too outlandish.
你们说得也太邪乎了吧
I think this is too Western.
我看这个是西洋风格
Too abstract.
太抽象
It doesn't reflect the essence of Peking University.
不能反映出我们北大的精髓
Peking University is the successor to the Imperial College's teachings.
北大者 上承太学正统
[Liu Bannong, Professor at Peking University]
[刘半农 北京大学教授]
The ancestral hall of this university
下立大学祖庭
is the highest institution that inherits
是传承我们中华文化传统的
our Chinese cultural tradition.
最高学府
Do you need to use
需要用这种西方的
this Western conception to embody it?
奇技浮巧来体现吗
Frivolous.
轻浮
Doesn't this image exactly have Chinese characteristics?
这瓦当形象不正是中国特色吗
Is there anything better than this?
还有比这厚重的吗
[Hu Shi, styled Shizhi, Professor at Peking University]
[胡适 字 适之 北京大学教授]
This is inauspicious!
这不吉利
Alright, alright.
好 好 好
Let each express one's opinions and contend with another.
各抒己见 百家争鸣
This is the ethos of Peking University.
这才是我们北大的风气嘛
Don't always let ourselves speak.
别总是咱们先生说
Exactly.
真是
Let the students speak too.
让学生们也说说
Zhongxia, come and speak.
中夏 你来说说
Zhongxia, come.
中夏 来
Speak.
说说
I think the seal is quite interesting.
我是觉得这个徽章挺有意思的
Look at the arrangement of these three "people".
你们看这三个人的排列
What about these two "people"?
这上面两个人呢
Like two students back-to-back.
像是两个背靠背的学生
What about the person below?
这下面一个人呢
[Deng Zhongxia, styled Zhongxie, Student at Peking University]
[邓中夏 字 仲澥 北京大学学生]
It's like a bowing teacher.
就像是弯腰弓背的老师
The teacher is lifting the two students with his shoulders.
老师用肩部托起两个学生
The teacher is thus willing to be a ladder.
老师呢 甘为人梯
The students have lofty aspirations.
学生志存高远
Peking University is passed on through the generations.
北大薪火相传
You take a look.
看看人家
Gentlemen.
诸位先生
I don't know what to say either.
我也不知道该说什么
I just think this design is very powerful.
就是觉得这个设计很有力量
I like a lot.
我很喜欢
Hello everyone, I'd like to ask
各位好 我想请问一下
which one is Mr. Chen Zhongfu.
哪一位是陈仲甫先生
Hu Shi!
胡适
Hu Shizhi!
胡适之吧
Hello Mr. Zhongfu.
仲甫先生好
I--
我
I know you went to Shanghai to meet me.
我知道您去上海接我了
Shizhi--
适之
There was something at home, so I had to get back in a hurry
家里有个事我就急着回去了
and make you come for nothing.
让您白跑了一趟
It was me who went to Shanghai.
是我去的上海
Am I that unconspicuous?
我就那么不起眼吗
You are Mr. Chen Zhongfu?
您是陈仲甫先生
Chen Duxiu, Chen Zhongfu is here.
陈独秀 陈仲甫在此
I-- I mistook you for someone else.
我 我认错人了
Mr. Zhongfu.
仲甫先生
Shizhi, I look forward to you.
适之 我可把你盼来了
I apologize.
抱歉 抱歉
Excellent!
太好了
Come, I'll introduce everyone.
来来来 介绍一下
This phony is Qian Xuantong.
这位假的是钱玄同
Welcome, Shizhi.
欢迎欢迎 适之
Liu Bannong.
刘半农
We've been waiting for you.
我们一直在等你
Shen Yinmo.
沈尹默
Hello.
你好
Finally, you're here!
终于把你盼来了
Gao Yihan.
高一涵
Morning.
早上好
Shenshu.
申叔
Professor Liu Shipei.
刘师培教授
Come and meet.
过来 见过
Hello, sir.
先生 你好
I'm Hu Shi.
我是胡适
Skillful, artful and frivolous.
奇技淫巧 轻浮已极
Zhongfu, this is my opinion.
仲甫 这就是我的意见
Shizhi, don't pay attention.
适之 不在意啊
This is not to say that you are frivolous.
这个 他不是说你轻浮
He's Liu Shipei.
他是刘师培
He-- he's sick.
他 他 他有病
He's still sick. He's still seriously ill.
他还 还在生病大病未愈
Okay, Yihan.
好了 那个一涵
Has the Shizhi's luggage arrived yet?
适之的行李到了吗
All the luggage checked in from America
从美国托运来的行李
has been moved to his single room.
全都搬到先生的单身宿舍里了
Good.
好
Let's go to the academic affairs office
我们大家一起先带着适之
with Hu Shi first.
到教务处办手续
Zhongxia, Xingang.
那个中夏 心刚
Ask some students
你们叫上一些同学
to bring tools
带上一些工具
to the Nanchizi
到那个南池子
single teachers dormitories.
单身教员宿舍那儿等着
Help Mr. Shizhi
帮着适之先生
tidy up his room.
一起把他那个小屋收拾好
Yes, let's go.
好的 走
Come, let's work together.
来来来 一起干活吧
Shizhi.
适之
We've met at last.
终于见了
Shizhi, come.
来 适之
Come.
来
Sit on the chair.
坐 上座
Thank you.
谢谢
Enjoy your meal, gentlemen.
二位客官 您慢用
I can't see you clearly when I sit across.
我坐过来 看不清你
I've been looking forward to you for half a year.
盼了你小半年
I finally got my wish to see you.
终于如愿以偿见到你了
Have you tried lamb hotpot?
涮羊肉吃得惯吗
Lamb hotpot.
涮羊肉
Not used to moving places.
吃不惯换地方
Quanjude roast duck.
全聚德 烤鸭
Let's go, we're going now.
走 现在就去 走
Sir, sir.
先生 先生
Lamb hotpot is great. I like it.
涮羊肉非常好 我喜欢吃
I can't eat it overseas.
在国外吃不到这些
Like it?
喜欢
I like it.
好 喜欢就好 坐
Sit down, sir.
先生 您快坐
What wine would you like to drink?
要喝什么酒
Erguotou.
二锅头
Pretty good.
挺好的
Good.
好
Since ancient times, men have hated each other,
自古人才千载恨
but they have always loved Erguotou.
至今甘醴二锅头
I'll pour it for you.
我给你倒上
I'll do it, sir.
我来 先生
Let me mix the seasoning for you.
我来给你拌调料
Alright.
好嘞
When eating lamb hotpot,
吃涮羊肉啊
the seasoning comes first.
这调料是第一的
I only learned it after I came to Beijing.
我也是到北京来之后才学会的
I'll do it, sir.
先生 我来吧
No, no, you can't.
不用不用 你不会
This salty taste is very particular.
这个咸淡非常讲究
Sir, that's very kind.
先生太盛情了
I, Chen Duxiu, while spending half my life wandering,
我陈独秀半生漂泊
have met quite a few scholars,
结识的饱学之士可谓不少
but most have little reputation,
但大多数浪得虚名
only my good brother makes me feel inferior.
唯有贤弟令我自愧不如
Several passages in the article "A Preliminary Discussion of Literature Reform"
一篇《文学改良刍议》
are like mountains and rivers.
几首自话诗犹如高山流水
It often makes me feel so relaxed and mesmerized that I forgot about all my honors and regrets.
常常令我心旷神怡 宠辱偕忘
And to be honest,
不怕你笑话
every time I write to you,
每次给你写信的时候
it reminds me of the Boya and Ziqi friends.
都让我想起伯牙子期
Thank you, sir.
谢谢先生
Come and taste the salty flavor.
来 尝尝 咸不感
You can add sesame paste if you feel it.
感了可以再加芝麻酱啊
When it's light, you can add chive.
淡了可以加韭菜花
Small bites, small bites.
小口 小口
Perfect.
合适
Good.
好
Come, eat some meat.
来 吃肉
Sir.
先生
Would you like some?
您 来点
Give me some.
给我
I wish you had already come.
你来了就好了
"New Youth"
《新青年》
would have been given to you and Shouchang.
就交给你和守常了
Honestly, New Culture in China
说实话 新文化在中国
is only be seen in its infancy.
还只能算是个婴儿
It may break at any time.
随时都有可能天折
Plus, Peking University is a complex place
再加上北大是集各种政治思潮
where all kinds of political thought agitate each other.
相互激荡的荟萃之地 复杂得很
You should have enough mental preparation.
你要有足够的思想准备啊
Sir, you mentioned Shouchang,
先生 您刚才说的守常
he's from Hebei.
是河北的
Li Dazhao.
李大钊啊
I believe that although you two have never met,
我相信 你们虽未谋面
you must become instant friends,
但一定一见如故
because I often dream
因为我经常做梦
the three of us together.
梦见我们三个在一起
You dreamed the three of us together?
先生还梦到我们三个人在一起
Yes, more than once.
对 不止一次
That's an extraordinary insight.
那是一位见识超人
Chivalrous, generous and elegiac people.
侠肝义胆的慷概悲歌之士
I often see the three of us in my dreams
我在梦中经常会看到我们三个
working together on "New Youth".
齐心合办 《新青年》
I also believe that the three of us
我也相信 我们三个
will definitely push forward the New Culture Movement.
一定会把新文化运动推动起来
Good.
好
For New Culture.
为了新文化
For your ideals.
为了先生的理想
Hu Shi is willing to do his part.
胡适愿尽微薄之力
Sir.
先生
I believe in one of your sayings.
我信奉您的一句话
"I won't talk about politics for twenty years
二十年不谈政治
but dedicate oneself to developing the enlightenment of people's wisdom."
致力于开发民智 启蒙思想
This is the way to save the nation.
这正是救国之道
To you.
我敬先生
Good.
好
Have ambition,
有志气
but this can't be done
但这不是只说几句气壮的话
by just saying a few words.
就能做到的
It's hard to not talk about politics for twenty years.
二十年不谈政治 谈何容易
The Zhang Xun Restoration
一个张勋复辟
has had tremenduous consequences.
就搅得天翻地覆
If he had really succeeded this time,
这次 假若他真的成功了
then "New Youth", New Culture,
那《新青年》 新文化
would have all been rejected.
都将会被拒杀
Honestly, sir,
说实话 先生
before returning home this time, my heart
这次回国以前我的心里
had always been uneasy.
一直是忐忑不安哪
But seeing you today,
直到今天 见到先生以后
this stone in my heart
我心里这块石头
has fallen to the ground.
才算落地了
Hmm.
嗯
Thank you, sir, for your encouragement and support.
先生 感谢您对我的栽培与提携
Be kind to me, sir.
先生对我恩同再造
Hu Shi has nothing to offer in return.
胡适无以回报
I am willing to follow you.
我愿意追随先生
I made up my mind when I returned home.
我在回国之时就已经下定决心
I have neither complaint nor regret.
无怨无悔
I will be a Huizhou camel to carry forward New Culture.
做一头弘扬新文化的徽骆驼
Good.
好
A Huizhou camel.
徽骆驼
Well put.
形象 贴切
Here.
来
Then let us two Huizhou camels follow the local customs
那就让我们两个徽骆驼入乡随俗
according to the old saying in Beijing.
按照北京的老话
Cheers.
咱走一个
Mr. Cai.
蔡先生
Hello.
你好
You're came.
您来了
Hello, shopkeeper Li.
李掌柜 你好
I--
我
I-- I would like to meet my collegues.
我 我来见一下我的同人
This way, please.
好 请
[Cai Yuanpei, styled Jiemin, President of Peking University]
[蔡元培 字 孑民 北京大学校长]
Shizhi.
适之
Mr. Cai came to see you.
蔡先生来看你来了
Sir.
先生
Please sit down.
快 请坐
Waiter, another pair of chopsticks!
伙计 再来一副碗筷儿
Got it!
好嘞
Hello, sir.
先生好
Zhongfu.
仲甫
I heard that there were two rabbits eating grass beside their burrow.
我是听说有两只兔子在吃窝边草
This old rabbit has arrived.
我这只老兔子就赶来
I'll order a large dish.
我打个牙祭哟
You won't object, will you?
二位不会反对吧
Come, sir, Shizhi.
来 先生 适之
Sit down and chat.
坐下聊
Alright.
好
I saw you two when I came here just now.
我刚才来的时候看见你们两位啊
You were elated.
说得兴高采烈的
What were you talking about?
在说什么呢
I and Shizhi were talking about
我在跟适之
New Culture and "New Youth".
聊新文化和《新青年》
The New Culture Movement is rising.
新文化运动啊方兴未艾
Every step, walking on thin ice.
每走一步呢 如履薄冰哪
Between you two,
你们二位
one is the master,
一位是主师
the other is the pioneer.
一个是先锋
What a perfect match.
真是珠联璧合呀
Come.
来
I hope you will unite sincerely with Peking University colleagues
希望二位与北大同人精诚团结
to run "New Youth",
办好《新青年》
leading the trend of history to carry forth a new generation.
领历史的潮流 开一代新风
Master Cai can rest assured that our generation will forge ahead.
蔡公放心 我辈自当奋勇向前
I'll just do a good job
我呢就给你们做好
by giving you some advice.
服务保障就行了
The vanguard of the movement depends on Shouchang,
冲锋陷阵还要靠守常
Shizhi,
适之他们呢
and Zhou Shuren.
还有周树人
Zhou Shuren is an
周树人那可是一位
incredible leader.
不得了的主将哦
Master Cai, Master Cai.
蔡公 蔡公
We thought of the same thing.
我们想到一块了
So, have you all agreed
怎么样 适之下学期开什么课
what classes Shizhi will teach next semester?
你们都商量好了吧
I--
我
Sir, the first course I want to teach is
先生 我想开的第一门课程是
history of Chinese philosophy.
中国哲学史
This is a little out of my expectation.
这有点出乎我的预料啊
Everyone wants you to teach Chinese literature.
大家都希望你来教授中国文学
That's above my expectation.
这期望很高的呀
Gentlemen, I think so too.
二位先生 我是这样想的
I think there is a misunderstanding
我以为现在国内国外
about the New Culture Movement
对于新文化运动
at home and overseas.
在认识上有个误区
I think that the New Culture Movement
以为新文化运动
is a complete negation of Chinese traditional culture.
就是对中国传统文化的彻底否定
In fact, New Culture
其实 新文化就是在
is created within the strong protection of traditional culture.
传统文化的强保里生成的
So,
所以
I want to make a systematic review
我想把中国思想文化的发展过程
of the development of Chinese ideology and culture
做一个系统的梳理
to help everyone clarify the relationship between the two.
帮助大家厘清二者的关系
This is also the content of my doctoral thesis.
这也正是我博士论文的内容
Well said.
说得好
Very well put.
很有针对性
I agree.
我赞成
There is one more thing I want to explain to Mr. Cai.
还有一件事情我要向蔡先生说明
Go ahead.
你说
My doctoral thesis failed in the first round.
我的博士论文第一轮没有通过
I'm making further amendments
我正在杜威导师的指导下
under Dewey's supervision
做进一步的补充 修改
and trying to pass the next round.
争取下一轮可以通过
I know this,
这个我知道
so don't emphasize it deliberately.
你就不要刻意强调就是
Well, since ancient times, men have hated each other,
好 自古人才千载恨
but what they have always loved is Erguotou.
至今甘醴还是二锅头
Another pot!
再来一壶
List of candidates for the school appraisal committee.
校评议委员会候选人名单
Chen Duxiu, Xia Yuanli, Wang Jianzu,
陈独秀 夏元瑮 王建祖
Wen Zongyu, Zhang Shizhao, Chen Yuan,
温宗禹 章士钊 陈垣
Ma Yuzao, Cai Yuanpei,
马裕藻 蔡元培
Wang Xinggong, Wu Mei, Qian Xuantong,
王星拱 吴梅 钱玄同
Tao Menghe, Shen Yinmo, Wang Shijie,
陶孟和 沈尹默 王世杰
Ma Yinchu, Hu Shi.
马寅初 胡适
Hello professor.
老师好
Hello sir.
先生好
Liu Wendian.
刘文典
Hello sir. Hello sir.
先生好 先生好
[Huang Kan, styled Jigang, Professor at Peking University]
[黄侃 字 季刚 北京大学教授]
What's the reason?
凭什么呀
There isn't any.
哪有这样的
Brother Shenshu.
申叔兄
You see what kind of list this is?
你看 这到底是个什么章程
Hu Shi, that yellow-haired child, is on the list.
胡适那个黄毛小儿榜上有名
I came behind last.
我等却名落孙山
What's wrong with this?
这成何体统
Peking University treats several masters of Chinese culture like this.
北大这样对待几位国学大师
We refuse to accept!
我们不服
Yeah! We refuse!
对呀 不服
Injustice!
不公平
Way out of line!
太过分了
That's not possible!
那哪儿行啊
Yeah!
对呀
What the hell is this?
什么玩意儿啊这是
They still have the final say later on.
以后还不都他们说了算呀
Yeah!
对呀
None of them!
一个都没有
Brother Shenshu.
申叔兄啊
What-- What's reason for this?
就是 凭什么
This gentleman can't shut his mouth.
这士可杀不可唇
I have to ask Mr. Cai for an explanation.
我等必须去找蔡先生讨个说法
If it's serious, go back to that lousy temple.
大不了 你再回那个破庙去
Let's go.
走
Jigang, I still feel sick.
季刚 我就是个病种子
I'm still in peace when I'm not on the committee.
不当这个议员我还落个清净
Shenshu!
申叔
Besides, I don't want to go back to that lousy temple.
再说了 我也不想回那个破庙去
You should go back to that lousy temple!
你就应该回那个破庙
How unusual for the two of you to come to me
二位一起来向我兴师问罪
full of disapproval and complaint.
挺新鲜的
Alright. How have you been wronged?
好吧 二位有什么冤屈啊
I, Yuanpei, will make it right for you.
我元培一定替你们主持公道
Mr. Cai, if I may ask,
敢问蔡先生
how was the list of committee members
这校评议会委员名单
on the school appraisal council produced?
是如何产生的
Ah, so it is this matter.
是这个事
I will explain.
那我跟二位说一下
After the Zhang Xun Restoration incident,
张勋复辟事件之后啊
I was requested by the Ministry of Education
教育部要求我们
to readjust the school appraisal committee membership
根据学校师资变动的情况
based on fluctuations in the number of qualified teaching staff.
重新调整校评议委员会的成员
[Gu Hongming, born Tangsheng, Professor at Peking University]
[辜鴻銘 名 湯生 北京大学教搜]
So based on the ministry's request
那么根据教育部的要求
the school council, after much deliberation,
校委会经过多次酝酿
have now put together a list of candidates
现在拿出了一个候选人的名单
for public feedback.
来张榜公布 征求意见
I suppose you both have already seen it.
想必二位都已经看了吧
What do you think? Please speak your mind.
有什么意见 直说无妨
I recall Mr. Cai once stated
我记得蔡先生曾言
academic performance
学术水平
shall be the basis of professorial appointments at Peking University.
乃北大聘任教授之重要标准
In light of this standard, we both believe
若按此标准 我等认为
there is a high proportion of chaff on the
此评议员候选人名单之中
proposed list of candidates for the appraisal committee.
多有溢芋充数之辈
Master Cai, such an appraisal committee
蔡先生 若如此评聘
would destroy the reputation of Peking University.
恐砸了北大之招牌
Mr. Huang Kan, please elaborate.
黄侃先生请明示
What sort of person is that Hu Shi?
那胡适是何许人也
He is merely a student who has just graduated.
其不过是一个刚刚毕业的学生
Peking University is China's highest institution of learning.
我北大乃中国堂堂最高学府
How could it possibly
焉能用一个
need a youth who can only sing a few farfetched nursery rhymes
只会唱几句不伦不类童谣的后生
on the appraisal committee?
做评议委员
Master Cai, allow me to be blunt.
蔡公啊 怨我直言
If all Hu Shi needs to do is say a few words of vernacular Chinese,
如果仅凭胡适说几句白话
speak a few foreign words
讲几句洋文
to become a professor, become a member of the appraisal committee,
就可以当教授 当评议委员
then let's not bother calling our Peking University as such any longer.
那我们北大就不要叫北京大学了
It might as well be the University of Vernacular Chinese.
叫白话大学好了
That's right.
对呀
Hu Shi
胡适呢
is an outstanding student from Columbia University.
他是哥伦比亚大学的高才生
A young talent recommended
也是我们北大
to Peking University from overseas.
从海外引进的青年才俊
Though he is young,
他虽然年轻
he has published extensively
但是著述甚丰
and has impeccable academic credentials.
学术造诣也很深厚
Amongst the younger students, he is very influential.
他在年轻人中间很有影响
So to choose him for the appraisal committee
所以选他做评议委员哪
also boosts the moral of the younger students.
也是对年轻人的一种鼓舞
So that reforms will more strongly take root.
让改革更深入人心哪
Master Cai, I myself studied abroad as a youth in England,
蔡公啊 我鸿铭少年留学英国
I was awarded a Master's degree in literature from the University of Edinburgh at the age of twenty.
二十岁获爱丁堡大学文学硕士
I am proficient in nine foreign languages.
我精通九门外语
If I'm not even qualified to be
如果我都不够资格
an appraisal committee member,
当评议委员的话
then how could Hu Shi, newly returned and without any achievements,
那他胡适刚刚回国 毫无建树
possibly deserve his position?
何德何能啊
It is true that you are world renowned.
你辜鸿铭确实是闻名四海
But you abetted the Zhang Xun Restoration,
但是你襄助张勋复辟呀
which has already aroused much popular indignation and anger.
已经激起了不少民愤
Furthermore, there are many joint letters from students and teachers
而且现在有很多师生都联名写信
calling for the removal of your teaching position.
要求取消你的教授资格
Do you think it's appropriate
你说如果这个时候
for you to be on the appraisal committee
要选你做评议委员会的委员
at such a time?
合适吗
Mr. Cai, haven't you always emphasized
蔡先生 您不是一再强调
that the most important standard at Peking University
北大用人最重要的是
is academic ability?
看学术水平吗
If we are judging on the basis of political orientation,
那若要论政治倾向
while I, Huang Kan, was waging revolution,
我黄促干革命的时候
what was Hu Shi even doing?
他胡适还不知在干什么呢
I really do take professional ability very seriously.
我的确非常看重业务水平哪
However, the country has certain stipulations.
但是 国家有规定
This reselection of appraisal committee members
这次校评议委员会的重选和调整
must abide by the clear cut policies set by the Ministry of Education.
教育部它就提出了明确的标准
One of which is that the appraisal committee members
其中就包括校评议委员会的委员
in terms of politics, must support republicanism.
在政治上要赞成共和的体制
Another, that teachers must have favourable personal attributes.
第二 为人师表要有良好的私德
A third, that must be representatives from different administrative levels, and so on.
第三 要有不同层次的代表等等
Which is why you two experts were not chosen.
你二位大师为何落选
I probably don't need to list
这个中缘由啊
the specific reasons one by one.
就不需要我一一细说了吧
I know the two of you are somewhat prejudiced
我知道你们二位对胡适呢
against Hu Shi.
是有些成见
To be quite honest, I had the same impression.
实不相满刚开始我也有同感
But after I met Hu Shi,
但是当我跟胡适见面之后
and conversed with him,
我听了他的谈话
his reasoning and his views
他的一些论点一些观念
dispelled my misgivings.
他打消了我的担忧和顾虑
Hu Shi is, after all,
胡适啊他毕竟是
a representative of new culture.
新文化的一个代表人物
Besides, Hu Shi is a brilliant student
而且美国实验主义大师杜威
of the American master of pragmatism, John Dewey.
胡适是他的高徒啊
It has extensive influence
在广大的学生中间
amongst many students.
有广泛的影响
I am planning to ask Hu Shi
我准备在北大呀
to prepare a lecture for us at Peking University.
请胡适给我们做一个演讲
I invite both experts to attend.
到时候请二位大师都去听
The level of his abilities
水平怎么样
will be clear upon listening.
一听 就不辩自明了嘛
Alright. When the time comes I will be certain to sing his praises.
好我老辜到时候一定去捧场
Great.
好
Mind your step.
二位好走
Come over here.
你来一下
Hurry and find Mr. Hu Shi.
这个你赶紧去叫胡适先生啊
Tell him to see me.
到我这几来一下
I have to talk to him.
我有事情要跟他说
Alright.
好
Please sit.
好 请大家坐下
Esteemed collegues,
各位同人
Zhang Xun does his restoration and Peking University is rocked by an earthquake.
张勋搞复辟 北大闹地震
For over three months
三个多月的时间
my students at Peking University
我北大的学子
was unable to focus on learning, on studying.
不能安下心来学习 读书
For over three months
三个多月的时间
my teaching staff at Peking University
让我北大的教员
was unable to use their energy on teaching, on giving classes.
不能集中精力来教书上课
For over three months
三个多月的时间
my collegues at Peking University
使我北大的同人
were unable to pursue their studies in peace.
不能平心静气地来研究学问
The very thought of it causes grief.
想起来令人痛心哪
Some have asked me, with all this turmoil,
有人问我 这个乱局之下
what is Peking University to do?
我北大怎么办
What is the fate of new culture?
新文化还搞不搞
Today, we've finally re-opened the school.
我们今天总算开学了
On the occasional of today's opening ceremony,
在这个开学典礼上
I have eight words for everyone present.
我有八个字告诉诸位
Our original intent is immovable, our commitment unwavering.
初衷不改 坚定不移
A few days ago, Dr. Hu Shi came to Peking Univerity.
前两天 胡适博士到北大来报到
He gave me an essay
他给了我一篇
that he published when he was in the United States.
他在美国发表的文章
Its title is "Against Studying Abroad."
题目叫《非留学篇》
Its topic is on the question
讲的就是
of how universities pursue knowledge.
大学如何研究学问的问题
I was very stimulated by reading it.
我阅读之后很受启发
Therefore, I've changed things up
所以 我们今天的开学典礼
for today's opening ceremony.
我变了个花样
I've invited Dr. Hu Shi
我请胡适博士
to give us a lecture.
来给我们做一个演讲
Its title is
题目就是
"The Relationship Between The University and Chinese Higher Learning"
《大学与中国高等学问之关系》
We invite Dr. Hu Shi to come onstage.
我们请胡适博士上台
You shall know the difference
我们回来了
now that we are back again.
请你们看分晓吧
This is a quote
这句话是
from the epics of Homer.
《荷马史诗》 当中的一句话
It means "Now that we are back again
意思是我们回来了
you shall know the difference."
请你们看分晓吧
What? What does this mean?
这 这是什么意思
I believe that these words also represent
我相信这句话也是此时此刻
what every scholar at Peking University feels at this very moment.
我们每一个北大学人的心情
A noble king ought also listen to the opinions of others
尊贵的王者也要倾听别人的意见
and proceed with caution.
谨慎行事
I give you a piece of advice.
我给你一句忠告
Do not forget it.
不要置之脑后
I'd like to ask Dr. Hu Shi what I've just said.
请问胡博士 我说的什么
Apologies, sir.
抱歉 先生
I truly do not understand what you said.
学生确实没有听懂先生所云
I just recited Homer
我说的是希腊语
in the original Greek.
原汁原味的《荷马史诗》
The meaning in Chinese is
它中文的意思是
A noble king ought also listen to the opinions of others
尊贵的王者也要倾听别人的意见
and proceed with caution.
谨慎行事
I give you a piece of advice.
我给你一句忠告
Do not forget it.
不要置之脑后
It is forgivable
胡博士不懂希腊语
that Dr. Hu Shi doesn't understand Greek
用英语朗读希腊的古诗
and recites Ancient Greek poetry in English.
情有可原
But if ancient Greek poetry is to be recited in English
但是 朗诵希腊的古诗
it ought to be the pure English
一定要用英国伦敦绅士
of a London gentleman.
纯正的英语
Your pronunciation is far too inept.
你的发音太不地道了
Entirely that of a commoner.
完全是下等人的发音
A proper London gentleman sounds like this.
真正伦敦的绅士是应该这样的
You shall know the difference
我们回来了
now that we are back again.
请你们看分晓吧
Ok?
明白
Wonderful!
好好好
This must be
想必这位就是
the illustrious Mr. Gu Hongming.
赫赫有名的辜鸿铭先生吧
To have received your instruction at our first meeting
初次见面就劳您教诲
is a great honour.
晚生十分荣幸
I am vey thankful for Mr. Gu's correction
我非常感谢辜先生
of my English pronunciation.
对我英语发音上的纠正
But today
但是今天
I use this quote from Homer
我引用《荷马史诗》 这句话
without regard for its language, its pronunciation, its tone.
我不在乎它的语言 语音 语调
I don't care whether it is said
我不在乎它是否是
in proper London English
正宗的英国人的伦敦腔
or with the pronunciation of a commoner.
还是下等人的发音
What I care about is
我在乎的是
the meaning it conveys.
它所表达的内容
Now that we are back,
如今我们回来了
you shall know the difference.
请你们看分晓吧
This statement is also what I wish to deliver to you.
这句话也是我想对您说的
This statement...
这句话
is what I wish to deliver to everyone sitting here as well.
也是我想送给在座的每一位
This is a statement from us at Peking University
这句话也是我们北大学人
towards an outdated China.
对一个旧的中国
A manifesto aimed at an outdated culture.
一个旧的文化的宣言
And it is also a solemn statement of commitment
也是我们对于办好新北大的一个
to the successful future of Peking University!
郑重的承诺